Pyle mss. II, 1921-1953 LMC 1879
Lilly Library
Pyle mss. II
1921-1953
Lilly Library
Pyle, Ernie, 1900-1945
LMC 1879
1 folio
1 Box 1 standard
The Pyle mss. II, 1921-1953, consist primarily of letters from journalist Ernest Taylor Pyle, 1900-1945, to his parents and aunt,
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Ernest Taylor Pyle (1900-1945), also known as Ernie Pyle, was a Pulitzer Prize winning American journalist. After attending Indiana University Bloomington, Pyle served as a newspaper correspondent and columnist who covered the lives of ordinary people as well as soldiers in World War II. Pyle was killed in battle at Ie Shima in the Pacific.
Scope and Content Note
The Pyle mss. II, 1921-1953, consist primarily of letters from journalist Ernest Taylor Pyle, 1900-1945, to his parents and aunt, written during Pyle's travels as a newspaper columnist and World War II correspondent. A poem written by Pyle while a schoolboy in Dana, Indiana is present, as well as three letters written to his family while he was a student at Indiana University. Other items include letters from various relatives, fellow journalists, and readers of his column, as well as a letter of October 21, 1884, from congressman Joseph Gurney Cannon to Pyle's grandfather Lambert Taylor. Pyle's travels are further documented by a photograph of him and his wife, with others, embarking on a trip of South America, and a map of South America with their various stops noted.
Correspondents include: Joseph Gurney Cannon, Rosamund (Zuck) Peters Goodman, Jack Rohe Howard, Roy Wilson Howard, Poe (Siebolds) Jones, Lee Graham Miller, Ernest Taylor Pyle, Geraldine (Siebolds) Pyle, Lincoln Saxton, and Edward Reilly Stettinius.
A typescript copy of Pyle's March 31, 1942, column from The Washington Post and a typed inventory describing each item complete the collection.
Related Material
Pyle mss., Pyle mss. III, Pyle mss. IV, Pyle mss. V, Pyle mss. VI, and Pyle mss. VII also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Acquisition Information
Acquired 1984
Gift. George Bales, Pepperdine College, Malibu, California via the School of Journalism, Indiana University, Bloomington.
American Literature--Indiana; Journalism; World War, 1939-1945
- Copy of original inventory (Box 1)
- 1884-1925 (Box 1)
- 1929-1937 (Box 1)
- 1938 (Box 1)
- 1939, Jan.-June (Box 1)
- 1939, July-Dec. (Box 1)
- 1940 (Box 1)
- 1941 (Box 1)
- 1942 (Box 1)
- 1943 (Box 1)
- 1944-1953 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Photographs (Box 1)
- Oversize correspondence., Apr. 1, 1922 (Box 2)